なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜日本人として
初めて月に立った➡
My brother, Hibito, has become the first Japanese person on the moon.
ひびと
我が弟 日々人｡
そうなん
月面で遭難するも➡
There was an accident,
ギリギリのところで
ぶじ
いちめい
無事に一命を取り留めた＞
but he managed to survive by the skin of his teeth.
⦅俺らは生きて
一緒に月面に立とうぜ⦆
We're going to stand on the moon together, alive!
Meanwhile, some of you may have forgotten this.
いっぽう
＜一方 すっかり
お忘れ…かもしれないが➡
But I, Nanba Mutta, have joined JAXA as an astronaut candidate.
わたくし
私 南波六太は宇宙飛行士の
こうほ
ジャクサ
候補としてＪＡＸＡに入社｡➡
ナサ
これからＮＡＳＡで行われる
きそくんれん
基礎訓練を前に➡
Before heading off for training at NASA,
けんしゅう
日本国内での新入社員研修と➡
I'm currently taking part in the new employee orientation in Japan.
オリエンテーションを
続けているのである！＞
And today, a special person has invited me
＜そして 今日
私は ある人に呼ばれ…＞
Sharon
To Mutta
Drop by and visit
when you're free.
I have something
to show you.
＜ある場所へと向かった＞
to come to a special place.
Space Brothers
I can no longer remember
what I tried to forget
When I peeked through the telescope
I realized that our world is tiny
It was a picture of infinity
It's not a one-time thing
We'll walk together
Once we've passed the clouds,
we will hold the world between our fingers
and keep what we lost in mind
#45 Five Blue Rangers
(進一)ウホンッ…｡
あの～ え～…➡
Uh,
so...
まず 天文学者として
言えることとして…｡➡
As an astronomer,
僕が新しい星を
見つけた時は まず➡
I promise that when I discover a new star,
その星に 君の名前を
付けることを約束しよう｡
I will name it after you.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)ホントに？
(進一)ああ｡だから➡
Really?
Yes, and to accomplish that,
そのためにはさ 君の協力も
必要になってくるだろうし…｡
I'll require your help.
(進一)なんていうか まあ…
２人で のんびり➡
So I'm saying...
Would you like to spend your life watching the stars with me?
星でも見ながら
暮らすのは どうかなと｡
それは つまり
僕と結婚してくれないかと➡
In other words,
I'm asking if you would marry me.
いうことになるんだけども…
どうだろうね？
How about it?
せいいっぱい
僕は精一杯で
こんな感じなんだけど…｡
This is the best proposal I can manage.
そうね…気に入ったわ｡➡
Yes...
I like it.
It's very appropriate.
進一さんらしくて｡
Your roundabout delivery...
とおまわ
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)その遠回しな言い方も➡
こんな星空の夜を選んで
言ってくれたことも…｡
And the fact that you proposed under the stars.
うれ
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)嬉しいわ｡
I'm so happy.
現在
Scissors, scissors, scissors, scissors.
Glue, glue, glue...
Glue.
Pat, pat, pat.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)フゥ…できた！
Finished.
最…っ高ね！
This is perfect.
Older Brother Also Becomes Astronaut
Received Medal for Saving
Oh, look at this, Tamura!
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)ねぇ 見て見て 田村さん！
とうとう 私のスクラップに
ムッタとヒビトが並んだわよ‼
I can finally have Mutta and Hibito side by side in my scrapbook.
(田村)本当ですか!?
Really?
わぁ…｡わぁ～
かな
ひとつ望みが叶いましたね｡
Another wish has come true for you.
嬉しいわ｡
I'm so happy.
でもこれ…六太さんには
見せづらいような…｡
But it would be hard to show this to Mutta...
Astronaut
Becomes
Older Brother
Also
Received
Medal For
Saving
Really?
(田村)だって 大きさが…｡
Well, their pictures are different sizes.
気に…しないわよ！
これくらい｡
He wouldn't let that bother him...
そうですね｡
You're right.
《どうだろう…？》
I wouldn't be so sure.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)大きさは問題じゃないのよ
田村さん｡➡
Size doesn't matter, Tamura.
２人が並んだってことがね…➡
The point is that they're beside each other.
最高！
It's wonderful.
≪おばちゃ～ん！≫
Hey, Aunt Sharon!
シャロンおばちゃん 来たよ～｡
Aunt Sharon, I'm here.
こんにちは～｡
Hello!
本当に!?
Really?
Yeah...
そんな大変なことに…
なってたの!?
He was in that much danger?
酸素が もれたなんて…あっ｡
His oxygen tank ran out?
記事には そんなこと
書いてなかったわよ…ホラ｡
The article didn't mention anything about that.
Look.
まあ 酸素切れの話は
日々人たちが地球に帰るまでは➡
Well,
they probably won't release any details until the astronauts are back on Earth...
こうひょう
さわ
公表しないだろうね｡騒ぎが
大きくなっちゃうから｡
That would only cause more confusion.
I see.
そっかぁ…そりゃそ～よね｡
You have a point.
田村さん！
Tamura...
世間にはヒミツよ…今の話｡
This is a secret from the rest of the world.
あっ ハイ！スイマセン｡
誰にも言いません｡
Yes, of course...
I won't tell anyone.
でも とにかく助かって
本当に良かったわ｡➡
But I'm so glad to hear that he's all right.
Your mother and father were probably very worried.
お母さん達も
心配してたでしょう？
Hmm? Mom?
いや…まあ…｡
Um,
well...
I'm home.
≪た～いま！≫
あ～ おかえり ムッちゃん｡
Oh, welcome home, Mu.
今 お笑いグランプリやっててね➡
They were just showing the Comedy Grand Prix.
“ティッシュ太郎ズ"が
優勝したわよ～！｢ニャンボ｣で｡
The Tissue Taros won.
With Nyanbo!
Tissue Taros
[TV]ニャンボ！
[TV](一同)ハッハハハ…｡
Nyanbo.
アッハハハ…ほら～！
アッハハ…｡
Watch...
｢ニャンボ！｣じゃねぇよ！
日々人が大変だったんだぞ！
This is no time for Nyanbo!
Hibito was in big trouble!
ＪＡＸＡから
連絡 来てね～の!?
(母)ああ～ 来たわよ｡➡
Regolith
Seasoning
Tastes Like
the Moon
Didn't you get a call from JAXA?!
Sure, I did...
な～んか穴に落っこちたって？
笑っちゃった｡ハハハッ…｡
He fell in a hole or something?
I couldn't help but laugh.
《ありえね～‼》
I don't believe it...
ハハハッ…｡｢ニャンボ｣より
にゃんぼか面白いわ 日々人｡
I think that Hibito is funnier than Nyanbo sometimes.
ウケるわ～｡アッハハ…｡
It's hilarious.
ヤツ
まったく よく 穴に落ちる奴だ｡➡
Seriously, he falls into holes all the time.
あしもと
昔っから“足下を見る"という事を
知らないんだ あいつは｡
Since childhood, he's never watched his step.
空ばっか見てるもんね あの子｡
That boy was always looking up at the sky.
(父)六太 お前も気をつけろよ｡
Mutta, you should be careful...
《もう…別にいいや これで…》
Yeah.
Whatever, I guess.
ニャンボ！
(母)わ～ 似てる！➡
Nyanbo!
That was really good! Nyanbo!
ニャンボ！アッハハハ…｡
現在
それで ムッタ
ＪＡＸＡでの仕事は どう？
So, Mutta...
How's your new job at JAXA?
ああ 今はまだ
｢仕事｣には なってなくてさ｡
Oh...
I'm not really doing any work right now.
なんかこう…
覚えることが６倍ぐらいある➡
It's like a driver's ed class, except with six times the material.
自動車教習所に
通ってる感じだよ｡
わぁ～ それ大変そう｡➡
Yikes, that sounds like a nightmare.
私 普通免許に２年かかったから
その６倍っていったら12…｡
It took me two years to get my license.
Multiply that by six, and you get twelve?
かかりすぎよ 田村さん｡
You're too slow, Tamura.
これは？
What's this?
そうそう！それをムッタに見て
もらおうと思って今日 呼んだのよ｡
Yes, yes...
That's what I wanted to show you today.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)やっと 予算が
こっちにも回ってきてね➡
We've finally received some extra budget,
ウチの天文チームが
長年 練ってきた計画が➡
so our astronomy team can start on a project that's been in the works for years.
ようやく 動き出すのよ｡
ぼうえんきょう
月面…望遠鏡｡
A lunar telescope?
月に望遠鏡 建てたら➡
You said that if we put a telescope on the moon,
はる
そうだい
地球より遥かに壮大な
宇宙が見えるって➡
we could see farther into space, right?
おばちゃん 言ってたよね｡
言ったね｡
I did.
俺が月に行って建てるよ｡➡
Then I'll go to space.
シャロン望遠鏡！
And I'll build the Sharon Telescope!
わかった｡楽しみにしてる｡
I understand.
I can't wait to see it happen.
現在
何か 思い出した？
Did you just remember something?
Yeah.
I still remember
ちゃんと覚えてるよ｡
that promise.
嬉しいわ｡
I'm happy to hear that.
(進一)シャロン！
やったよ シャロン！
Sharon!
I did it, Sharon!
君と結婚して２年…ようやく
しょうわくせい
新しい小惑星を見つけたぞ！
It's been two years since we got married,
and I've finally discovered a new asteroid.
ホントに!?
すごい！おめでとう‼
Really?
That's amazing... Congratulations!
ありがとう｡
Thank you.
何か 思い出した？
Did you just remember something?
ああ ちゃんと覚えてるよ｡
Yeah.
I still remember.
約束通り その星に
シャロンと名付ける！
As promised, I'll name it "Sharon"!
嬉しいわ…｡
I'm happy to hear that.
現在
＜私が１３歳で
日々人が１０歳の頃に➡
When I was thirteen and Hibito was ten, Sharon's husband,
シャロンの旦那さん
金子進一博士は病気で亡くなった＞
Dr. Kaneko Shinichi, died of an illness.
＜２人の夫婦生活は
たった４年だけだった＞
They were only married for four years.
＜シャロンが夢見る
月面望遠鏡は➡
The lunar telescope Sharon dreams of
それまでの
宇宙望遠鏡よりも➡
will let us see distant areas of space, still to be uncovered.
しんうちゅう
遥かに遠い深宇宙を
見ることができる＞
＜きっと世界の天文学は
ひやく
大きく飛躍し➡
Astronomers worldwide would have access,
to make important, new discoveries.
新たな発見が相次ぐはずだ＞
＜だけど シャロンにはきっと
もっと ささやかな願いが…＞
But Sharon is probably hoping for something more mundane.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)ねえ 見て見て
ムッタ！ヒビト！
Hey, look at this, Mutta, Hibito...
Huh?
な～に～？
どうしたの～？
What is it?
これが ウチのハカセが発見した
小惑星よ｡その名も｢シャロン｣｡
This is the asteroid my husband discovered.
It's called Sharon.
へぇ～いいな～！
どれ？
That's cool!
Which one?
This?
これ？
《小っちぇ～》
It's tiny!
小っちぇ！
Tiny!
フフッ そう！
小さくて全然見えないでしょう？
Yes, it's so small, you can barely see it.
That's why I want to put a telescope on the moon,
だから いつかね この星の姿が
大きく見えるように➡
月面に望遠鏡をつくりたいのよね｡
to see a bigger picture...
どんな星かな…｡
I wonder what it'll look like.
現在
よっしゃ！気合い入れてくぜ｡
Okay!
Time to get serious!
《シャロンが
あの星の姿を見たがってて➡
Sharon is working to build a telescope because she wants to see that asteroid better.
望遠鏡をつくろうとしている》
What should I do?
《そしたら俺は
何をすんのか…》
I made that decision long ago!
《もう…決まってる！》
⦅嬉しいわ 覚えててくれて⦆
I'm so happy that you remembered.
⦅当～然！⦆
Of course...
《つい この間までは➡
It wasn't so long ago that I wanted to forget about that promise.
忘れててほしいなと
思ってたんだけどね…》
⦅数年後 うまくタイミングが
合えばいいわね｡➡
In a few years, if the timing works out,
the telescope will be ready.
この望遠鏡の準備が
整う時期と…➡
ムッタが宇宙へ旅立つ時期が…⦆
Right around when you head into space.
A promise with Sharon.
《シャロンとの約束…》
A promise with Hibito.
《日々人との約束…》
Hey...
《なんだ…俺には➡
I have promises to keep!
やるべき事が
ちゃんとあるな！》
Yes,
なすだ
(茄子田)え～…ねぇ…まあ➡
when I look at the five of you, it reminds me of that...
君達５人を見てるとねぇ
わたくしは何だか➡
アレを思い出すんだよね～｡
あのね ホラ あれよ…➡
Yeah, you know what I mean?
あの～ほら…おお！
You're like the five Power Rangers.
戦隊ヒーロー５人組をさ｡ね！ね！
Right? Right?
Yeah, I like that idea...
いや～まあ 何かいいよねぇ｡
Each of you has your own color.
いろ
５人５色とでも言うべきかねぇ｡➡
Makabe would be Red, since he's a leader type.
まかべ
真壁君はね あの｢レッド｣だよね
リーダー的だしね｡➡
And I just noticed he's in the middle.
気付けば真ん中にいるもんねぇ｡
んでまあ あの➡
And Kitamura has a bright disposition, so she should be Yellow.
きたむら
北村さんは ほら 明るいから
｢イエロー｣が似合うよねぇ｡➡
Nitta's a cool player, so he gets to be Blue.
にった
新田君はクールだからね
もう｢ブルー｣に決定｡➡
Itou is Pink, of course.
いとう
伊東さんはもちろん｢ピンク｣よね｡
(せりか)《やった！》
Yes!
And you, uh, Nanba...
(茄子田)ほんで 何だっけ 君は…
南波君…➡
Yes, you're green.
はい ミドリ｡
《ミ…ミドリ!?》
Green?
《ミドリかぁ～ ビミョー…》
Green, huh?
That's an iffy color.
いや～ピッタリだね この配色！
Yes, my casting is perfect!
《せめて｢グリーン｣って
言ってくれよ…》
Why don't I get the English word?
むらさき
(紫)じゃあ 俺は
何色っすかね？理事長｡
Then what color would I be, Director?
わかってるよ わかってるよ もう｡
｢パープル｣は君のもんだよ 紫君｡
I know, I know...
Purple's all yours, Murasaki!
《それ決めて ど～すんだ…》
Does this even matter?
オッホン とまあ
皆さんのね イメージカラーが➡
So now that we've decided on a color to fit each of you, I have some bad news.
決まったところでね
残念なお知らせです｡
Well, I have a present for you.
え～まあ これからね 皆さんに
プレゼントを配りますがね➡
But unfortunately, it only comes in one color.
残念ながら色は
一色しかありませんの…｡➡
本当はね あの～
戦隊風に５色にしたいって➡
To be honest, I requested five different colors,
頼んでみたんだけどね
まあ ダメだってさ｡➡
but that was a no-go.
昔っから 基本は
この色と決まってんだってさ｡
Traditionally, they always use this color!
こま
はい 小町っちゃん
配っちゃってね｡
Okay, Koma... Pass them out.
こまち
(小町)よっしゃ！まかしときぃ‼
Sure! I'm on it!
《ん…？誰…？》
Huh?
Who's she?
えっと～六太はんは…
これやね よいしょっ！
Let's see...
This is yours, Mutta.
There.
Oh, thanks...
あ ど～も ど～も…｡
(小町)はい お嬢ちゃんは これ｡
ありがとうございます｡
This one is yours, young lady.
Thank you very much.
《お…これは…まさか…！》
Could this be...
んん～ それでは 皆さん➡
Okay, everyone... Unwrap your presents.
開けてみてちょうだいね～
オープン オープン オープ～ン！
Open, open, open!
(ケンジ)やった！
カッコいい…！
All right!
It's so cool...
It's...
本物だ！
It's the real thing!
すげ～名前入ってる！
Wow, it has my name on it!
(北村)アハハ 靴もあるよ！
It even comes with shoes.
いやいやいやっ ええやんかっ！
にお
みんな よう似合てるわぁ！
Well, well, well.
You all look very sharp.
《うわ… ぽい…》
Yeah...
《なんか…➡
This is it...
ぽくなってきた‼》
Now this is more like it!
ほしか
(星加)《この瞬間は
いつ見てもいいね…》
I always enjoy this moment...
I feel really bad, everyone...
ん～ねぇ なんか
申し訳ないね 皆さん｡
I wasn't able to stop them from making you all Blue Rangers.
およ
わたくしの力及ばず 全員
青レンジャーになっちゃって｡
(北村)《いや 青でいいよ…》
No, blue is fine.
(ケンジ)《よかった 青で…》
I'm glad mine is blue.
《青でよかったぁ～》
Good thing they stuck with blue...
《せりかさんのピンクは
見たかった…》
I'd have liked to have seen Serika in a pink one.
Oh, I forgot.
あっ ああ そうだ 忘れてた！➡
I want to introduce the manager who will be taking care of you guys.
え～これからね 皆さんの
身の回りの世話をしてくれる➡
マネージャーを紹介します｡はい｡
The mother of JAXA, Komachi.
ＪＡＸＡのオカンこと
小町さんです｡
Hello.
(小町)ど～も～｡
My name's Komachi, written as "small town."
｢小さい町｣で小町やで｡
よろしくやでぇ～‼
Nice to meet you!
小柄だけどね
たくましいよ 彼女は｡
She may be small, but she's strong.
I drink vegetable juice each morning.
(小町)毎っ朝
青汁 飲んでるからやね｡
(紫)さて みんな！
ジャンプスーツを着て➡
Okay, everyone.
I'm sure you're excited, putting on your jumpsuits for the first time.
気分が高まってきたところだろう｡
その意気込みのまま➡
But there's no break because we're leaving tomorrow morning.
我々は 明日の朝 出発する｡
わかってんね｡
Got it?
いよいよ ヒューストンでの
合同基礎訓練が始まるよ！
It's finally time to start our joint training in Houston.
During joint training,
(紫)合同ってのは つまり
各国の新人宇宙飛行士が➡
astronaut candidates from across the world will come to NASA,
ＮＡＳＡに集まって 一緒に
同じメニューの訓練をする｡➡
all following the same training regimen.
低コストで しかも短期間に一流の
飛行士を育てる為のプランだが➡
It's a means to train a high rate of top astronauts at low cost.
You'll be meeting your talented peers from around the world.
つわもの
そこで出会う 各国の強者共は
君らと全くの同期生だ｡➡
君らの一番の仲間になり➡
They will become your best comrades and worst rivals.
一番のライバルになる奴らだ｡
そのうち遊びに行くからね
ムッちゃん｡
We'll visit some time, Mu.
To see Apo.
アポに会いにな｡
クゥン…｡
Right.
行ってきます！
I'm off!
The stones out in the fields
are worn down by their daily existence and disappear
That's their trial
When will we be able to resist fate?
Before you lose all hope
and say that we can't win against gravity
go without stopping
past the goal line
You have such strong convictions
Leave your footprints on this Earth
Maybe their tiny length will cause a miracle in the end
Give us a magnificent jump
Run now and do it
Jump past all you see overhead
This is your stride
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#46 Number One Restless Guy
＜私達 宇宙飛行士候補生は
ついにＮＡＳＡへ！＞
The astronaut candidates finally arrive at NASA!
(バトラー)＜ホールド君｡今回の
訓練教官は 君に…＞
Bold, you've been assigned as a training instructor.
＜こいつがヒビトの兄貴か｡
ふぬけた顔をしてる｡➡
This is Hibito's older brother?
He looks rather dim.
Naturally, he has no military experience.
当然 軍隊経験もなし｡➡
弟に後れをとってる上に
この 締まりのない ふぬけ顔｡➡
He's a step behind his little brother, and he looks like a fool.
It's clear that he's a lost cause.
救いようのないノロマだと
すぐわかる＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
Number One Restless Guy.
Since I've been selected as a training instructor,
＜私が訓練教官に選ばれた以上
軍隊式で いかせてもらう＞
I'll give them the military treatment.
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
Do you recognize this person?
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
誰これ？
Who is that?